The title is not hyperbole, and that's
not only because fasting has been
discovered to supercharge fat loss
through a fascinating mechanism in your
cells, but because it lends further
evidence to something that I predicted
over 4 years ago when I looked like
this.
I know. Yikes. And then
someone looks at me now and says,
"Yikes."
Anyway, so what am I talking about? I'm
talking about this brand spanking new
study. Basically it shows fasting
activates a new mechanism of fat loss.
You see, your fat cells store millions
of fat molecules, and when we fast,
meaning no calories consumed, our fat
cells release fat molecules into the
blood to be delivered to our organs to
feed them. There's a lot between there,
but that's the gist. And for your fat
cells to release stored fat molecules,
they usually rely on a process called
lipolysis. However, when researchers
looked at the enzymes, the functional
proteins responsible for this lipolysis
process, they actually discovered the
amount of the enzymes was diminished,
not elevated, which is puzzling because
if they're needed for the releasing of
fat, why would they not be elevated?
It's because the fat cells are
increasing other proteins that are not
usually linked to fat breakdown. In
fact, that's why the title of this study
is called non-canonical because these
proteins are involved in
autophagy. In fact, we can actually see
it here in these microscope images. I'll
add an image of a fat cell here to
follow along. The blue is the nucleus of
the cell, the red is the identifying
marker of the fat cell, and all that
black area is where the millions of fat
molecules are stored. The green is an
identifying marker of autophagy. If you
focus on the inset at the far right, the
white arrow is pointing to activation of
autophagy vesicles in the fasting
condition. To be clear, they also show
average data corroborating this image.
So this is the exciting part for me
because years ago I discussed some other
research that showed that autophagy may
be elevated related to fasting. But
specifically in immune cells involved in
fasting. So I'll get into that in just a
little bit. For now, just know that
fasting does not increase the normal fat
loss mechanisms, but increases autophagy
to help in fat release from the fat
cells. But here's the thing, what was
actually discovered through some elegant
experiments is that fasting forces
changes upon the body. Meaning initially
fat breakdown does occur through normal
lipolysis, but as the fast progresses,
autophagy becomes a bigger and bigger
player. Essentially, there is a
metabolism handoff as the fat cells
begin upregulating, producing more
autophagy proteins to create autophagy
vesicles to break down fat. So one
question is,
why? Why not just stick with the usual
lipolysis pathway? Well, I have my own
hypothesis, and the researchers present
another perspective. Essentially, they
believe that the stimulus for fat loss
is different between the initial period
of the fast and the prolonged periods of
the fast. Initially, fat loss is
triggered by hormones binding to the fat
cells, telling them to activate
lipolysis and by releasing fat. However,
as the fast progresses, the trigger
changes away from a predominantly
hormonal origin, which begins the
handoff to the autophagy system.
Basically, both fat breakdown systems
respond to different stimuli. Initially,
it's hormonal, later it's less so. Now,
my perspective doesn't actually
contradict that, and it's even mentioned
to a degree by the researchers
themselves. Essentially, I think that
the initial stages of a fast, your body
is still partly dependent on glucose, so
sugar metabolism, as it metabolizes the
glycogen stored glucose inside the
tissues. However, once that is depleted,
there's a much greater need to rely on
fat metabolism. So the fat cells have to
dump fat like their lives depend on it.
Think of it like initially they have the
dam half open, but deeper into the fast,
the dam fully opens. That's when these
large autophagy vesicles
can capture thousands of fat molecules
that will be far more efficient at
breaking down that fat for release.
Without it, the bottleneck is the sheer
amount of enzymes necessary to go
through the canonical or the normal
lipolysis pathway. In in essence,
the lipolysis system is too slow. It
requires a more powerful force to step
in and help, autophagy. By the way, and
just as a quick correction to myself,
the true word is lipophagy, not
autophagy, but autophagy is just more
recognizable. I just had to get that off
my chest. Okay, fascinating. But how
does this relate to our immune cells?
Remember, I alluded to some previous
studies looking at autophagy on fat in
immune cells during fasting. And beyond
that, these results that we've gone over
are only possible
to be studied to this degree in animals.
So does this actually translate to
humans? Now, I'd like to get more into
that, especially the immune angle, in a
bit. But before we do that, there's some
fascinating consequences of fasting
caused autophagy on the liver, how it
suctions fat out like a vacuum cleaner,
as well as some other metabolic effects,
and some more details on what happens in
us mere mortals, the human folk. If
you're interested in a deeper dive on
the whole topic, plus an accompanying
article, and all these perks right here,
like uh live sessions that I'm doing
soon and on a regular basis, check out
the Physionic Insiders. It's my personal
research platform, and there's a
community of Insiders that we all
discuss together. So consider joining,
the link is in the description. That
rude interruption dismissed, the reality
is that we can't do all these same
experiments in humans. So we do more
exact experiments in animals, and then
we look for clues in humans. And what
clues we find. When looking at people
who fast for 10 days, we discover
several clues, specifically shown here.
We're looking at four genes that are
tightly related to control autophagy.
I mean, lipophagy in human fat tissue.
In orange and gray are the gene
expressions, or the amount of the gene
reading occurring before the fast, and
the red dots are the results that are
after the fast. For two of the genes,
the genes that were most studied
throughout the study, though I've mostly
spared you from the tedium, were
elevated with fasting. So this creates a
correlation that what we see in animals
is possibly also the case in humans.
That said though, they took things one
step further by taking fat samples and
exposing them to autophagy inhibitors.
As expected, the autophagy blockers
slowed fat release significantly,
further substantiating these results in
humans. So the point here is that while
not foolproof, there is some evidence
substantiating that autophagy is heavily
involved in human fasting for mass
release of fat from the fat cells. I
mean, come on, you can't say that isn't
really freaking cool. I mean, that is so
wild. Here's the thing though, as I
alluded to, this wasn't the first study
that was discussing these kinds of
things. Though other studies were
focused on the fascinating crosstalk
between your fat cells and your immune
cells. Essentially, and there's plenty
more detail to this that I'll link for
you, but essentially fat cells will
export their fat in vesicles as well. In
doing so, immune cells invade into the
fat tissue, and it's assumed that they
take up these fat vesicles, and they
deal with this potentially through
increasing autophagy of their own. Now,
how freaking cool is that? What a
synergy.
Well, look, none of this is saying that
you have to fast, and
it's really not telling us anything at
all applicable. It's just telling us
about a fascinating discovery, and that
discovery is that fasting supercharges
fat loss by employing autophagy systems
in our fat cells to rapidly break down
stored fat. Now, promise me you won't
make fun of my hair. You pinky promise?
If you'll promise, I'll link the first
video on fasting and increases in
inflammation. No, not a bad thing. It's
based on what we went over here, but I
was younger, dumber, and had fewer
jokes, so bear with me.
I'll put it here and in the description,
and I have a follow-up video going into
even more detail on autophagy inside
immune cells right here. Either that you
choose will lead to the other, so it
doesn't really matter which one you
choose to watch first. Thanks for
nerding out with me, and I'll see you
over there.